Finding Aid for Francis Fowler McKinney papers, 1941-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Francis Fowler McKinney papers 1941-1972
McKinney, Francis Fowler, 1891-1972.
4 linear feet
851766 Aa 2
Historian and biographer from McMillan, Michigan. Correspondence, notes, and manuscripts concerning the research, writing and publication of "Education in Violence," a biography of Civil War general George H. Thomas; also research materials on other Civil War topics, travel narratives, and miscellanea.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Francis F. McKinney (donor no. 3129 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Francis McKinney was born February 25, 1891 in Washington D.C. He attended the University of Michigan (1911-1913) where he was managing editor of the Michigan Daily; he then graduated from the U-M Law School in 1916. During World War I, he served as an ensign aboard the USS Carolina, 1917-1919. After the war, he was employed in a variety of professions, as a surveyor, in advertising, as a journalist and writer, and in the automobile industry. In 1949, he retired, moving to Sagitaw Farm in Lakefield township, Luce county in Michigan's Upper Peninsula.
In his retirement, McKinney devoted himself to historical research and to the writing of historical monographs, particularly on the Civil War period. His biography of Civil War general George A. Thomas was published by Wayne State University Press in 1961. Some of his shorter articles were published in the Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review. McKinney's biography of Revolutionary War general Francis Marion remained unpublished at the time of his death on December 7, 1972.
The McKinney collection is comprised mainly of his historical research and writings, mainly on Civil War topics and the career of General George H. Thomas. The series in the collection are: Personal and miscellaneous; Correspondence; Historical research and writings; and Travel writings.
Subjects:
Authors, American--Michigan.; Education in Violence: The Life of George H. Thomas and the history of the Army of the Cumberland.; McMillan (Mich.); Thomas, George Henry, 1816-1870.; Voyages and travels.; Travelers.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Custer, George Armstrong, 1839-1876.; Dwellings--Virginia.; Flags.; Medical aspects of war.; Military officers.; Monuments and memorials--Washington (D.C.); Thomas, George Henry, 1816-1870.; Virginia--Dwellings.; Walker, Mary.; Washington (D.C.)--Monuments and memorials.; Women--War.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal and miscellaneous
  - Biographical and miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Minutes and by laws of the Sagitaw Corporation (Box 1)
  - Tax materials, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated and 1941-1970, 8 folders (Box 1)
- Historical research and writings
  - History of Fort Wayne, Michigan, 1851-1861, 1961 (Box 1)
  - "Trial of General Buell" Undated (Box 1)
  - "The First Regiment of Michigan Engineers and Mechanics" 1955 (Box 1)
  - "Michigan Cavalry in the Civil War" 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - "The Capture of Jefferson Davis" (Box 1)
  - Review of "A Civil War Artist" 1957 (Box 1)
  - "The Northfield Raid and its Ann Arbor Sequel" 1954 (Box 1)
  - Brig. General Elon John Farnsworth 1959 (Box 1)
  - "New Evidence of Drunkenness Tags Grant as a Security Risk" undated (Box 1)
  - Review of "Stonewall Jackson, The Good Soldier" 1958 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript to "Francis Marion: Unique Warrior, 1780-1783", 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Manuscript to intended volume on the life and career of Lt. Howard B. Cushing (different titles), 3 copies (Box 2)
  - Manuscript to "Education in Mobility; A study of the Northern Cavalry in the Civil War" (Box 2)
  - Education in Violence
    - Reviews 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - Indexing 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Revisions of Chapter 18 1959 (Box 2)
    - Publication, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
    - Wayne State University Press, 1956-1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Research note cards, 1 box (Box 2)
    - Manuscript to text (incomplete), 14 folders (Box 3)
    - Photographs collected by McKinney for use in his biography of Civil War general George H. Thomas, Education in Violence (Box 3)
      (photos include portraits of Thomas and other Civil War military figures; photographs of Thomas' home in Virginia (taken in 1951) and the Thomas monument in Washington, D.C.; also portrait of Civil War era physician, Mary Walker)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Travel writings
  - Manuscript to "Abroad during the Suez Crisis" 1959, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Manuscript notes to "Abroad during the Suez Crisis" 1959 (Box 4)
  - Manuscript to "Through twelve nations by car in 1961 and 1962" (Box 4)
  - "Mexico and the Far West" 1960 (Box 4)
  - Western trip, 1965 (Box 4)